have you ever wanted to make an open
world well today I'll be showing you all
of the steps involved to make this scene
you're seeing right here in just 5
minutes and this is updated for urp and
unity 6 so this tutorial should work for
several years to come let's start
totally fresh in the unity Hub click new
project and be absolutely sure to use
Universal 3D for the template name your
project and click create when you open
Unity it might look like this I'm going
to choose the 2x3 layout under window
and then use one column layout here and
hierarchy right click and create a
Terrain click on your terrain then in
the paint terrain tab we choose raise or
lower terrain I'm going to use a brush
size of about 400 select this noisy
brush and then set my opacity down to
about 10 or 15 then we're going to do
what I like to call a three part pass
first make your Coes pass where we paint
big features second scale down your
brush size and opacity and paint in some
smaller features all around third choose
smooth height get a bigger brush and
then smooth your whole terrain repeat
that until you're happy we need some
assets so I drop two links for you below
in the description first add the low
poly environment asset from the asset
store next add the starter assets
firstperson controller back in unity
open the package manager click on my
assets then search low poly environment
click import to project you'll get
another popup then click import again
now to do the same thing for the
first-person controller go ahead and
delete your main camera and open up the
starter assets folder find the nested
player unpack prefab and drag it into
your you're seen it has this mobile UI
by default if you don't need that I
suggest just deleting the UI canvas and
the UI Event Systems inside the prefab
now you can select the parent and freely
position it on the terrain surface at
this point you should be able to press
play and freely walk around now let's
make this terrain a bit less ugly this
is really important so open up the
polytope studio folder then inside
environments there's a folder named SRP
open that up and double click the most
recent urp file here then click import
to convert to urp materials click on
your terrain then select paint texture
click edit terrain layers add layer and
select ground layer two for the grass
now let's add some 3D grass go to your
paint details tab go into edit details
and add a texture for the detail texture
I'm going to choose PT grass O2 add this
then get a big brush and paint over the
entire area that you want grass but you
might notice it doesn't fill in past a
certain point so that's because we need
to go to terrain settings in in increase
the detailed distance don't go too
overboard here I think 150 to 200 is
okay so we don't kill performance click
back on our grass and edit details make
the Min and Max width and the height a
little bit smaller we can also slide up
our detail density here until it looks
nice and full maybe somewhere around 2.5
then choose a light and dark color for
your grass to fit your project now if I
go into play mode our ground color
doesn't really match our grass so we can
fix this by going to our paint terrain
tab selecting our grass layer than
choosing a color tint drag around colors
until it visually matches the bottom of
your grass next let's go into the paint
trees tab click edit trees and add a
tree for the tree prefab I'm going to
use the PT Pine tree3 Green and be very
careful to select the prefab with the
solid blue box icon next to it now we
can use this awesome terrain feature
named Mass Place trees I'm going to
choose 10,000 trees then click place and
you'll randomly distribute a ton of
trees all across your tur brain now I
don't think our trees match our color
palette so I'm going to edit the tree
prefab double click the prefab to open
it up in the scene view then click on
the game object ending with
lod0 then open up the Shader in the
inspector here we can customize the
color of our tree to match our scene I
use the Color Picker and choose a light
and dark part of the grass for our top
and bottom color while we're here let's
also add a capsule collider component so
that we can't run through the trees you
can slide down the radius so that it's
only around the trunk to give it a good
hitbox to improve performance click on
the parent object here and Slide the
cold LOD group to the left I would
recommend setting this to around 6 or 7%
for good performance next go to window
rendering and dock your lighting panel
and under environment I'll choose the
Skybox named PT Skybox mat then I'll
check fog and for the color a tip here
is to use the Color Picker again and
choose a color low on the horizon to
match the color palette of your project
I'm going to dial down the intensity
just a bit to about
0.2 and that's looking pretty good at
this point I'm going to add a few more
objects in our paint tree panel like
rocks mushrooms and poppies and using a
brush size of about 200 or so you can
click to paint on some of these objects
around your player I'm also going to
pull this glowing ruined rock into our
scene and to Showcase this let's make
one last amazing change to finish out
the scene click your main camera then
check postprocessing and your Global
volume select Aces for tone mapping then
set your Bloom threshold to 1.3 and
intensity to around three next add a
color adjustment postprocessing effect
I'm going to check this post exposure
and turn it up a bit to brighten up our
scene and at this point we're done let's
check out our final demo for this
beautiful open world nature
scene remember to subscribe like and
comment to boost me into the good algor
universe and I'll see you all next time
peace